# 我今天路過兄弟家
I passed by my buddy's home today.
# 嗯
Yup
# 路過兄弟家就把他 他家的雞抓過來了 給它烤了
I passed by my buddy's home and I caught his chicken. We're going to grill it now.
# 兄弟叫我 拿去拿去拿去
He said, "Take it! Take it! Take it!"
# 那 我那兄弟對我很好的哦
That, that buddy treats me really well.
# 那太好啦
That's wonderful!
# 那我有你這個兄弟就當當於有很多個兄弟了是吧
So having you as a buddy means that I have thousands of buddies, right?
# 對呀
Exactly!
# 嘿
Hey!
# 不是你吃的哦
It's not for you!
# 我要把它對半劈開 不劈開烤不了
I need to cut it open in the middle, otherwise we can't grill it.
# 我給你拉住
I can hold it for you.
# 這樣就可以啦
It should be alright now.
# 可以
Yea!
Good!
# 這 那個腿上面的肉要改一下
The, the leg may need to be sliced a few times.
# 要不然很難熟
Otherwise it would take a long time to get it done.
# 這頭要不要 這頭不要
Do you want the head? I don't think we want it.
# 頭 都可以
Head? Whatever...
# 等下烤熟了給
We can grill it and give...
# 不用烤熟
No need to grill.
# 給狗吃嘛
give it to the dogs.
# 生的給它吃啊
You give them raw?
# 生的給它吃
Yup! Give them raw.
# 很 很難得可以嘗到你做的
I am so, so privileged to have a chance to try your cooking.
# 很難得
It's really a privilege.
# 甚麼難得 經常來 經常做給你吃
What privilege? Visit me more often. I am at your disposal.
# 很好吃的哦
It tastes really good.
# 小心小心
Careful, careful!
# 誒耶
Eyeh?
# 掉了一塊皮
I dropped a piece of skin.
# 把它端起來 不要被狗吃掉了 等一下
Put it there. Don't let the dogs eat it.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 嗯 這個 鹽要稍微放多一點
Um, here, we need slightly more salt.
# 最近口味比較重
I prefer stronger taste recently.
# 是嗎
Really?
# 對
Ya
# 再加點料酒
Put some cooking wine as well,
# 再加點油
and some oil.
# 嗯對
Yea, right!
# 我都知道你還有 還要放醬油
I also know that you have, you want to put some soy sauce too.
# 醬油
Soy sauce
# 加點醬油它 才好看
It looks good, only with soy sauce.
# 夠不夠
Enough?
# 不夠 再加一點 加點
No. Put more.
More
# 好 可以
Ya! Alright!
# 你這傳統 老配方
Your traditional, old formula.
# 對
Ya
# 熟悉的味道
Familiar taste
# 要提前腌一下
It needs to be marinated first.
# 用它的肝來做掃
I use its liver as a br...
# 掃子
brush.
# 爆它的肝
Burst its liver.
# 沒掃子 沒掃子的就只能用
I don't have a brush. Without a brush, I can only use,
# 它的心
its heart.
# 它的心也在
Its heart is here too.
# 它的心也在一起
It's heart is together with it.
# 心怎麼那麼小
Why is the heart that small?
# 心大一點
I hope it were larger.
# 加點生薑
Put some ginger,
# 再加點辣椒粉
and some chili powder.
# 沒有辣椒粉不好吃
I won't taste good without chili powder.
# 辣椒粉你隨便放就行
Chili powder is completely up to you.
# 等一下小哥吃下了
But Mr. Cameraman might not be able to stand it.
# 沒事 他現在也很能吃辣椒
Doesn't matter. He can eat chili now.
# 他 他現在很能吃辣
He, he can eat very spicy food now?
# 是啊 他現在很能吃啦(辣？)
Yup! He can eat really spicy food now.
# 練出來了嗎
He trained up himself, right?
# 是啊
Ya!
# 你這個手藝 見長了喔
Your skills, have been much polished.
# 哪裡
No way.
# 真的
It's true.
# 給它洗洗腳
Let me wash its feet.
# 洗洗腳
You said wash its feet?
# 給它按按摩
And give it a massage.
# 腌個半個小時 我們再來烤
Marinate it for half and hour, then we can start grilling.
# 那行
'kay!
# 我們到外面
Let go outside,
# 看一看先
and take a look first.
# 好
Alright!
# 那個腳後面來慢慢烤
Let's grill the feet later.
# 很快熟的
It won't take long.
# 這溫度很高的哦
The temperature is really high, you know?
# 它這裡一封的話 這個熱量全部轟上來
When it's covered here, all the heat rushes to the top.
# 辣椒一邊多一點一邊少一點 這樣就大家都可以吃
I put more chili on one side and less on the other. Then everybody can enjoy.
# 喜歡吃辣的在這邊 不喜歡吃辣的在這邊
This side is for those who like spicy food. And this side is for those who don't.
# 嘿嘿 分配好啦
He he, it's well distributed.
# 分配好啦
Exactly!
# 我家的那個 那個
Our, our, well,
# 烤豬那個架子啊
our rack for grilling pig.
# 焊了半天
We made it for half a day.
# 這 自己焊的哦
You mean, you made it yourself?
# 嗯 要不下次我給你焊一個
Yea! How about making one for you next time?
# 可以啊 我買個電焊機來
Sure! I'll buy a welding machine.
# 正好你這裡還有豬
It would be perfect, as you have pigs here.
# 可以呀 那兩條小公豬要把它幹掉 今年
No problem! The two little boars need to be eliminated, this year.
# 那個 那個小公豬養來沒用的
It's, it's no use keeping the little boars.
# 又不下崽
They don't give birth anyway.
# 好東西是慢慢地烤出來的 要烤出它的靈魂出來
Good food is always grilled slowly, so that the soul can shine.
# 你這個
You ah...
# 搞到精華了你 啊
you know the essence of it.
# 精華
Essence...
# 這個雞兄弟養了很久了
My buddy had been keeping this chicken for a long time.
# 早就 早我就想叫他送給我了 我又不肯
I had been always asking for it. But he said no.
# 看 今天路過他那裡是不是
Look! I passed by his home today, right?
# 那麼小他當然不肯啦 要雞養大一點
Of course he didn't want to. It's so small. It can still be bigger.
# 邊烤邊 邊烤邊
Grill and, grill and, grill and....
# 吃啊 沒事
Just eat. No worries.
# 都在看
They're watching.
# 你看兩個 兩個好吃狗
Look at the two, two greedy dogs.
# 給 給它吃一個好吧
Shall, shall we give it a piece?
# 給它吃一點
Give it a bit.
# 噫呦 來
Yiyo! Come!
# 香不香
Is it good?
# 你別說 你這個雞 真的好吃誒
No kidding. Your chicken is really tasty.
# 他這散養雞來的
His chickens are all free-range.
# 被我們兩個扒完了這個皮
The skin would be all taken by both of us
# 呦 這塊好
Yo! This piece is good.
# 我來逗下來狗
Let me play with the dogs.
# 華農哥我覺得你很會烤這種東西哦
Mr. Huanong, I feel that you're really good at grilling these stuffs,
# 很會烤哦
good at grilling.
# 還好了吧
Not too bad, perhaps?
# 教教我唄
Can you teach me?
# 想吃就烤 我們這邊
Here, we grill whenever we want.
# 烤出來 烤出來經驗
That's why you're, you're so experienced.
# 熟能生巧
Practice makes perfect.
# 多烤點
Grill more.
# 把剛哥家的那些雞呀 鴨呀 通通烤掉
Grill all the chickens, ducks, everything at Gang Ge's place. (Ge: Honorific title for Wang Gang)
# 剛哥都是教我炒的 (烤︰漆二娃的「炒」應該可以精準一點)
Gang Ge teaches me stir-frying,
# 怎麼炒 怎麼做
the skills of stir-frying.
# 也行啊
It's good as well.
# 炒的也很好吃啊
Stir-frying is also very tasty.
# 你要不要嘗一下 這雞皮
Do you wanna try? Try the skin.
# 拿著吃
Take it.
# 挺好吃的這個
It tastes rather good.
# 嗯
Um!
# 真香
It smells great.
# 嗯 原來雞皮這麼好吃啊
Um! I didn't know that chicken skin tastes so good.
# 可以再吃一點
You can have more.
# 好啊
Sure!
# 就是等你這句話
So you say it.
# 你不說我都不好意思問來吃
Otherwise, I would seem too greedy if I ask for more.
# 沒事
No worries.
# 多吃點
Just eat.
# 你才來 等下都 都吃 吃光掉啦
So you come finally. We're about, about to, to finish it.
# 吃光啦 還有大把誒
Finished? There's still a lot.
# 現在我把這個料給你搞一下
I'm now getting the sauce ready for you.
# 你看看 腿都被你哥掰斷啦
Look! The leg is already cracked by your brother.
# 你哥小時候 你們誰調皮一點
Who were naughtier when you were kids? You or your brother?
# 一看就知道 哈哈哈
Isn't it too obvious? Ha ha ha!
# 肯定我哥啊
Certainly it was my brother.
# 額 他在這裡不好說
Eh! You don't wanna say too much when he's around.
# 小時候你們誰挨的打誒的多一點
Who were beaten more often when you were kids?
# 都不挨打的
We were never beaten.
# 都不挨打
Never beaten
Never
# 那太好啦
That's great.
# 上次我哥烤豬排都是
Last time when by brother was grilling ribs, it was also
# 越烤越小塊
getting smaller and smaller.
# 邊烤邊吃是吧
You must have eaten a lot when you were grilling, right?
# 我哥走開一下給我偷吃了一塊
I stole a piece when my brother was away for a while.
# 我來
My turn
# 我弟一來烤 把我的烤
I just give it to my brother for a while, but he...
# 你幫你烤這個啊
Yea, he helped you.
# 稀巴爛了
He smashed it.
# 稀巴爛
Smashed?
# 加點孜然啊
Put some cumin powder.
# 這個孜然
It's cu..
# 這孜然
cumin powder.
# 你先讓一下嘛
Can you just move away a bit?
# 這裡 這裡 好 好
Here, here, good, good.
# 嗯 可以 null
Um! Alright
# 搞定 可以吃啦
Done! Let's start!
# 這一坨肉好大啊
It's a huge piece of meat.
# 別掉了哦
Don't drop it.
# 吃大塊的
Take the larger one.
# 啊 直接一人一塊啊
Ah! Simply each of us has a piece?
# 一 一人一塊
One, one each.
# 那多不好意思啊 我吃這麼大塊的
Oh, I would seem too greedy. Mine is so large.
# 來者 來者是客
You're, you're our guest.
# 好 謝謝啊
Alright! Thanks a lot!
# 這麼大一塊肉
W a huge piece of meat!
# 嘗一下
Have a try.
# 嗯 很好吃喔
Um! It's really tasty.
# 給點給狗吃 它望了很久了
Let me give a bit to the dogs. They've been watching for a long time.
# 來
Come!
# 給一點 不用給那麼多
Give them a bit. Don't give too much.
# 好
Okay!
# 嗯 這個 母狗給它多吃一點
Um! The, the mother can have a bit more.
# 母狗功勞最大是吧 生了這麼多小狗
The mother should be the most acknowledged, right? She gave birth to so many puppies.
# 對 都是它兒子
Yup! They're all her children.
# 我 我 這 這一塊可能有一斤多
My, my piece perhaps weighs more than a pound.
# 差不多了
I think so.
# 要不先 先把它放著 我們把那個豬排烤了
Shall we first, first put it aside and grill the ribs?
# 好
Alright!
# 那個豬排 走
The ribs. Let's go!
# 拿那 拿那個盤子裝起來
Put it, put it onto the plate.
# 加點鹽 這個排骨
Put some salt, the ribs.
# 這個排骨很好吃的哦這個排骨
The ribs are really tasty, you know.
# 再加點醬油
Put some soy sauce too.
# 不用啦 這個 已經提前腌製啦
This one, no need. It has already been put beforehand.
# 辣椒粉
Chili powder
# 嗯 辣椒粉
Um, chili...
# 哎呦 給我搞太多啦
Ayo! I've put too much!
# 你這個手 抖了放多啦
Your hand shivered. That's why you've put too much.
# 沒事
Never mind.
# 再辣我都能吃
Spiciness never bothers me.
# 再搞點這個油
Put some oil as well.
# 這個油要搞多一點
It needs a bit more oil.
# 你竹鼠是不是經常這樣子烤
Is it how your bamboo rats are always grilled?
# 是啊
Yup!
# 這樣很漂亮的
It's now very pretty.
# 準備 下鍋
Ready! Go!
# 漂亮
Pretty!
# 繼續
Part two!
# 沒事的 這個灰都可以吃的
No worries! The ashes are also edible.
# 嗯 可以
Um! Alright!
# 先把這個
First, let me,
# 先拿去 這樣打開
put it here and lay it flat.
# 好
Good!
# 一塊小肉 別掉了
A small piece of meat. Don't drop.
# 這個豬有多大呀
How big is the pig,
# 多重
how heavy?
# 這個豬 五十斤左右
The pig is, about 25 kilograms.
# 五十斤
25 kilograms.
# 哇 這五十斤 它排骨也太小了吧
Wa! 25 kilograms, the ribs are far too small.
# 是啊
Yea,
# 就一點點排骨
just a bit of ribs.
# 我記得我們上次烤那個野豬 排骨起碼要比這個長一寸
I remember the wild boar that we grilled last time. The ribs were at least an inch longer.
# 長 長這個麼
It's, it's that much longer.
# 長那麼多
So much!
# 嗯
Um!
# 沒事 (註︰不知道這句有甚麼意思)
No problem.
# 你是不是每次燒烤的時候它們都在
Is it whenever you grill anything, they're always,
# 它們都在旁邊
they're always staying next to you,
# 都圍成一個圈圈是吧
forming a circle?
# 對啊
Indeed.
# 太好玩了 你們這裡養這麼多狗
It's so much fun that you have so many dogs here.
# 上次都還不止呢 這一次
It's even more than last time. This time,
# 這一次真的是
this time, it's really...
# 一地都是狗
Dogs are everywhere
# 吃的是
So they eat...
# 樹根啊 菜葉子之類的
Roots or veggie leaves or whatever.
# 它那個肉質比較好
So the texture is really nice.
# 這個肉質
The texture...
# 這 特別好
Yup! It's exceptionally good.
# 它就有點類似野猪肉咯
It's quite similar to the pork from wild boar.
# 差不多
I think so.
# 你知道這一點在市場買要多少錢嗎
Do you know how much it costs in the market?
# 七八十塊 上百塊
Seventy or eighty, or a hundred RMB.
# 估計都要百多塊錢
I think it's over a hundred.
# 這裡差不多兩三斤了
It's almost a kilogram and a half here.
# 烤排骨
Grilled ribs
# 看了都讓人流口水
Simply watching it is already mouth watering.
# 嗯 我都已經流口水了
Um! I'm already drooling.
# 把這個架子掀開
Let me put away the net.
# 小心掉下去哦
Don't drop it.
# 我扶著
Let me hold it.
# 等下掉下去都沒得吃啦
If it drops, game over.
# 為甚麼家 你家的豬
Why are, why are you pigs,
# 如此好吃
so tasty?
# 我花了那麼大的心血 把它養肥
I've put so much effort in feeding them, in letting them grow.
# 天天吃那菜葉子 吃了幾噸菜葉子了
They have veggie leaves everyday. They've already eaten up several tonnes of veggie leaves.
# 是嗎
Really?
# 是啊
Yep.
# 這個斷了
It's broken.
# 那 那個鋼網 快點放上面去
The, the steel net, put it on top!
# 差一點就要吃灰了啊
We almost needed to eat the ashes.
# 來 現在再慢慢烤一下
C'mon. Let's grill it for another while.
# 好
Alright!
# 哇 這個太香啦 這個
It's smells simply wonderful!
# 嗯 可以哦
Um! Not bad!
# 就有那種香味 那種 香豬肉的味道 好像 (註︰「香豬」好像沒有怎麼的譯法，這款豬叫「環江香豬」所以乾脆叫"Huanjiang pig"啦)
It's the aroma, I mean, the aroma of Huanjiang pork, it's like...
# 你看一說吃的這些 狗狗就來啦
Look! The doggies come once you say something about eating.
# 好啦 本期視頻就到這裡吧 我們
Alright! Shall we end the video here? We,
# 我們要吃排骨啦
we need to enjoy the ribs.
# 我們要吃排骨啦 吃相有點不好
We need to enjoy the ribs and we don't have really good table manner.
# 對呀
Exactly!
# 好啦 拜拜啦
Alright! Bye!
# 唉 別掉哦
Ay! Don't drop it!
# 誒 掉了吃不成
Ay! It would be too bad if it drops.